Hello.
مرحبا،
This is my first trip,
هذه هي رحلتي الأولى،
first time in life I'm outside of the walls of Gaza.
فللمرة الأولى في حياتي أكون خارج أسوارغزة ،
I'm so happy to be here.
وأنا سعيدة جداً لأنني هنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
My ambition always was to be a pilot, to fly a plane,
كان طوحي دائماً أن أكون طيارة وأن أقود طائرة ،
to feel free to fly the sky, to touch the sky.
وأن أشعر أني حرة وألمس السماء،
But that didn't happen.
ولكن ذلك لم يحصل ،
Simply, I live in Gaza, there is no airport.
لأنني ببساطة ،أعيش في غزة ولا يوجد مطار هناك ،
All borders are closed on every side.
وكل الحدود مغلقة بجميع الإتجاهات .
We live in one of the biggest prisons in the world.
نحن نعيش في واحد من أكبر السجون في العالم.
The only thing I can do is just to look up to the sky.
والشيء الوحيد الذي أستطيع القيام به هو النظر للسماء.
On some days, we are lucky if we have electricity
ونعتبر محظوظين ذلك اليوم الذي يكون لدينا فيه كهرباء
for four or five hours.
لمدة 4 أو 5 ساعات.
When it's cold, we make a fire on the front or on the roof of our homes.
وعندما يكون الجو بارداً نقوم بإشعال النار أمام أو على أسطح منازلنا.
Sometimes we make food, too.
وأحياناً نقوم أيضاً بطهي الطعام .
My job in Gaza is to arrange everything for journalists who come to my homeland
عملي في غزة هو ترتيب كل شيء للصحفيين الذين يأتون إلى وطني
to tell the stories about what's going on in Gaza.
لنيقلوا الأخبار والقصص التي تحدث في غزة.
Many mornings, I had to go to the border area
في الكثير من الصباحات كان علي أن أذهب إلى المنطقة الحدودية.
to collect a journalist.
لأحضر صحفيا واحدا.
If anything should happen to the journalist,
فإذ حدث شيء للصحفي ،
or if the journalist decides to cover a story
أو أن الصحفي قرر تغطية موضوع معين
the government doesn't want us to cover,
لا تريد الحكومة منا تغطيته ،
bad things could happen.
فقد تحصل أشياء سيئة.
Navigating through my country helping journalists,
التنقل خلال بلدي ومساعدة الصحفيين،
filmmakers, news crews, is my working life.
و صناع السينما،وطواقم الأخبار هي ببساطة حياتي العملية.
I believe my success comes from building a relationship
وأنا أعتقد أن نجاحي يأتي من خلال بناء علاقات
not only with journalists and the news crews,
ليست فقط مع الصحفيين والطواقم الإخبارية،
but also with the communities in the Gaza Strip.
ولكن أيضاً مع المجتمعات في قطاع غزة .
These communities who don't want their stories to be told,
هؤلاء الناس الذين لا يريدون لقصصهم أن تنتشر،
I never looked to them as stories or numbers.
ولم يحدث أنني نظرت إليهم كمجرد قصص أو أرقام.
But like me, they are human beings.
ولكن أنظر إليهم ،كما أنظر لنفسي بأنهم بشر .
I have built up many relationships over 10 years.
لقد بنيت العديد من العلاقات خلال ال 10 سنوات.
And guess what?
وخمنوا ما حدث ؟
This gives me the chance to get access to people,
أتاح لي هذا الأمر الفرصة للوصول للناس ،
to stories that others can't.
ولقصص لا يستطيع أناس اَخرين الوصول إليها.
In some certain situations, I feel, as a woman, I have more power.
وفي بعض المواقف ،أشعر كامرأة بأن لدي قوة أكبرمن كل شيء.
Many male journalists in my society,
بعض الرجال الصحفيين الموجودين في بلدي ،
they want to cover a story about drug addiction in my country.
يريدون أن يغطوا قصة حول إدمان المخدرات في بلدي.
That problem started when the Gaza tunnel was being built.
المشكلة بدأت عندما تم بناء أنفاق غزة.
With the siege on Gaza,
مع حصار غزة،
tunnels brought people all the basic needs
ومن خلال الأنفاق كان يتم تزويد الناس بحاجاتهم الأساسية
like food, building material, other stuff we needed.
مثل الطعام ومواد البناء والأشياء الأخرى التي نحتاجها.
But not anymore, because the Egyptian side flooded them up with water
ولكن ليس بعد الآن، لأن الجانب المصري قام بغمر هذه الأنفاق بالماء
and they are not working anymore.
ولم تعد تعمل نهائياً .
Drugs were being smuggled,
كان تتم عملية تهريب المخدرات ،
and many young people got addicted, too.
و قد أدمن الكثير من الشباب عليها أيضاً .
In the tradition of the Palestinian society,
في تقاليد الشعب الفلسطيني،
it's forbidden for men to enter the household.
يعتبرمحرماً للرجال الغرباء بالدخول إلى بيوت الأهالي،
So, no male journalists get the story.
ولذلك لا يوجد صحفي رجل حصل على القصة.
But I did.
ولكني حصلت عليها.
I have a wonderful husband,
لدي زوج رائع ،
a wonderful husband who supports me
زوج رائع يقوم بدعمي
despite all the criticism he gets from the society.
بغض النظر عن كل الإنتقادات التي وجهت إليه من قبل المجمتع .
He's at home now with my two kids,
وهو الاَن في البيت مع أبنائي الاثنين.
and I have another one that's growing in here.
ولدي ابن اَخر هنا،في بطني .
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
When I'm working, I call him every two hours,
عندما أكون في العمل أتحدث مع زوجي كل ساعتين،
and he knows if he doesn't hear from me,
وهو يعلم أنه إن لم يتلق اتصالا مني،
he should call my contact,
فسيقوم هو بالاتصال بالشخص
the one who gives me access to the story,
الذي أتاح لي الوصول إلى القصة،
which is the one who I trust.
وهو الشخص الذي أثق فيه.
One of the times in Gaza,
في يوم من الأيام في غزة،
during the kidnapping of the British journalist Alan Johnston,
خلال عملية اختطاف الصحفي البريطاني آلان جونستون،
I was asked by an American magazine
طلبت مني مجلة أمريكية
to set up a meeting with the kidnappers in Gaza, and I did.
بترتيب لقاء مع الخاطفين في غزة، وهذا ما فعلته.
The journalist covering the story and I
طلب مني و الصحفي الذي غطى القصة
were asked to meet outside of his hotel.
أن نلتقي خارج الفندق الذي يقيم فيه.
They came, they picked us up in a black van with black windows,
جاءوا ووضعونا في سيارة سوداء ذات زجاج أسود.
they were wearing masks on that day.
وكانوا يرتدون أقنعة على وجوههم ذلك اليوم.
And they drove us away, far away in the middle of a field.
وقادوا السيارة بنا بعيداً في وسط أحد الحقول.
They took our cell phones
أخذوا هواتفنا المحمولة
and we did the interview with the kidnapper outside in that field.
وقمنا بإجراء المقابلة مع الخاطفين في الخارج في ذلك الحقل.
I was so scared that day,
لقد كنت خائفة جدا ذلك اليوم،
a day I will never forget.
يوم لن أنساه ما حييت.
So, why do I do what I do?
إذن، لماذا أفعل ما أفعله؟
I do it because I believe if I didn't,
أفعل ذلك لأنني أعتقد إنه إن لم أفعل،
a huge part of the story about Gaza will be missing.
فسوف نفقد جزء كبيرا جدا من أجزاء القصة عن غزة.
There are some more stories I could tell you about my country.
وهنالك قصص أخرى بإمكاني أن أخبركم بها عن بلدي.
And not all of them are bad.
وليست كل هذه القصص سيئة .
I love my country, despite the terrible situation we live in --
أحب بلدي ،بغض النظر عن الوضع المزري الذي نعيشه--
siege, poverty, unemployment --
الحصار ،والفقر ،والبطالة--
but there is life.
ولكن هنالك حياة .
There are people who are dreamers and amazing people full of energy.
وهنالك أناس حالمون وطموحون أناس مذهلون ممتلئون بالحماس.
We have wonderful music, and a great music school.
لدينا موسيقى جميلة ،ومدرسة موسيقية عظيمة.
We have parkour dancers who dance in the rubble of their homes.
لدينا راقصو الباركور الذين يرقصون تحت حطام منازلهم.
And Gaza is the only place in the Arab world
وغزة هي المكان الوحيد في العالم العربي
where Muslims and Christians live in strong brotherhood.
حيث يعيش المسلمون والمسيحيون في جو أخوة متين.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )
During the time of war,
خلال الحرب،
the hardest part for me is leaving the house early in the morning,
كان الأمر الأكثر صعوبة بالنسبة لي هو مغادرة منزلي في الصباح،
leaving my children.
و ترك أولادي .
I take a picture of them everyday
لقد كنت التقط صوراً لهم بشكل يومي ،
because I never know if I will make it back to them.
لأنني لا أعرف إذا كنت سأستطيع العودة إليهم.
Being a fixer and a journalist is difficult and dangerous in Gaza.
أن تكون صحفياً وترتب اللقاءات الصحفية هو أمر خطير في غزة.
But when I hear the sound of the shelling or the sound of the bombing,
ولكن عندما أسمع صوت القصف والقنابل،
I just head straight toward it,
أقوم بالتوجه مباشرةً نحوها،
because I want to be there first,
لأنني أريد أن أكون أول من يكون هناك،
because these stories should be told.
لأن مثل هذا القصص يجب أن تروى.
When my children were small and we heard the sound of the war,
عندما كان أطفالي صغاراً وكنا نسمع صوت الحرب،
I used to tell them that they were fireworks.
كنت أخبرهم بأنها مجرد أصوات لألعاب نارية.
Now they are older, they understand.
والاَن كبروا وأصبحوا يعون مايجري .
I do have terrible nightmares
أعاني من كوابيس فظيعة ،
because of all that I witnessed during war times,
بسبب كل الذي ما شهدته خلال الحرب،
especially these lifeless bodies of young children.
خصوصاً الجثث الهامدة للأطفال الصغار.
I still remember a little girl, her name is Hala.
ما زلت أتذكر طفلة صغيرة، اسمها هالة.
She's the only survivor from her family.
وكانت الناجية الوحيدة من أهلها.
Her picture will be with me forever.
ستظل صورتها عالقةً في ذهني للأبد.
I will never forget her.
ولن أنساها أبدا.
I'm proud that I can stand here and be here today with you.
أنا فخورة بأنني أقف هنا و بوجودي معكم اليوم.
I'm proud that I can tell you stories, sad and happy,
فخورة لأنه بإمكاني أن أخبركم قصصاً حزينة وسعيدة،
stories about my small corner of the world, Gaza.
قصص عن زاويتي الصغيرة من العالم ، غزة.
I'm proud that I am the first female fixer working in Gaza.
وأنا فخورة لأني أول منسقة صحفية تعمل في غزة.
And the funny thing is they call me Mr. Rambo in Gaza.
والمضحك في الموضوع أنهم يدعونني في غزة بالسيد "رامبو ".
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
I hope one day, I will get the chance to tell the stories of all other women,
أتمنى أن أحصل على فرصة يوماً ما لأخبر قصصاً عن كل النساء الأخريات،
all other amazing women I know in my country.
كل النساء المذهشات اللاتي أعرفهن في بلدي.
I hope that one day I can help other women in my country
أتمنى يوماً ما أن أساعد النساء الأخريات في بلدي
to be fixers like me.
ليصبحوا منسقات صحفيات مثلي.
And of course sometimes, I feel I can't do this work anymore,
وبالطبع أحياناً أشعر أنني لا أستطيع إكمال مسيرتي في هذا العمل،
it's just too much for me.
لأن ذلك صعب بالنسبة لي.
But I remember these words:
ولكنني أتذكر تلك الكلمات :
"Don't limit your challenge, but challenge your limit.
"لا تقم بتقليص تحديك ولكن تحدى حدودك.
Don't allow others to stand in front of your dreams."
ولا تدع الاَخرين يقفون عائقاً أمام أحلامك. "
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق )